Alright, okay, בוקר טוב tov. *Boker Tov*. We're on today's דף *Daf*
קל"ח *Kuf Lamed Chet*, 138. We took up the bottom of קל"ז
עמוד amud, ב' *Kuf Lamed Zayin Amud Bet*,
and we're at the following. And we're dealing with like מתנה על
מנת להחזיר *matana al mnat lehachzir*, which was somewhat related, I mean,
you know, like loosely related to קנין kinyan פירות *kinyan perot*, קנין
kinyan הגוף *kinyan haguf*, and what's considered real ownership of something and
so on. And whether מתנה על מנת להחזיר *matana al mnat lehachzir*
are you really enough of an owner? You know, we know that
sort of classically in the case of לולב *lulav* and אתרוג *esrog*,
but it really is introduced here by רבא Rava *Rava*. And the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* even deals with like that the person might have
the ability to be מקדיש *maktish* it based on what the condition
of returning it is. Is it returning something usable or just returning
the thing itself? Okay, now we pick up with four lines from
the bottom,
and again, a little like loosely connected here. So, אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel*, says Rav Yehuda in the
name of Shmuel, four lines from the bottom קל"ז עמוד ב' *Kuf
Lamed Zayin Amud Bet*. Says Rav Yehuda in the name of Shmuel,
הכותב נכסיו לאחר Ha-kosev nechasav l'acher, *hakoteiv nechasav leachair*, somebody writes over
his property to somebody else. Okay, this may whether this is a
מתנת שכיב מרע mattnas shuchiv mera. *matnat shchiv meira*, let's assume, or
let's assume it's a normal קנין kinyan. *kinyan*. It sounds like from
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* even a straight normal קנין kinyan *kinyan*. מתנת
בריא *matnat bari*, exactly. Okay, ואמר הלה V'amar hala, אי אפשי בהן
iy efshi bahen, *v'amar hala iy afshi bahen*. So
I say, I write down, Michael, I'm being מקנה makne *makneh* to
you all of my property קנין אגב *kinyan agav* of this piece
of land, and I give you the שטר shtar *shtar*, and Michael
looks at the שטר shtar *shtar* whatever and he says, 'What the
heck is this? I don't want your property. אי אפשי בהן *iy
afshi bahen*. I like to earn my own keep through this world.'
So קנה *kana* מתנת בריא *matnat bari*, you took the שטר shtar
*shtar*, it's yours. Now that's a little bizarre, right? I mean, come
on. How are you supposed to be קונה koneh *koneh* something without
your רצון *ratzon*? So let's keep on reading.
He reached for the שטר shtar, *shtar* first, he told you what
it was, and then...
Well, it's not exactly clear. Let's keep on reading. ואפילו עומד וצווח
*v'afilu omeid v'tzoveiach*, even if he's standing and yelling and saying I
don't want it. ורבי יוחנן אמר לא lo, קנה *v'Rabbi Yochanan amar
lo kana*, he's not קונה konah *koneh*. So now we gotta make
some sense of the position of קנה *kana*. So אמר רב אבא
בר ממל *amar Rav Abba bar Memel*, ולא פליגי *v'lo pligi*, they
don't debate, top of קל"ח עמוד א' Kuf Lamed Ches Amud Aleph
*Kuf Lamed Chet Amud Aleph*. כאן בצווח מעיקרא כאן בשותק מעיקרא ולבסוף
צווח *kan b'tzoveiach meikara kan b'shoteik meikara u'lesof tzoveiach*. So one is
Michael from the very beginning says, 'What the heck is this? I
don't want this nonsense. I don't want your money.' Okay, and then
of course there was never his רצון *ratzon*. The other is he
takes it, says 'Oh,' you know, and he looks at it and
he thinks about it and then maybe his wife says something to
him, he says, 'You know what? Forget it. I don't want it.'
Okay, but anyway, I made it a little more dramatic, okay? But
even if it's like, the question is how much is מעיקרא *meikara*
and how much is ולבסוף *u'lesof*? If it took him ten seconds
to react, sometimes you're in such a state of shock, is it
anything אחר כדי דיבור *achar k'dei dibur*? You know, what exactly is
the שיעור *shiur*? Okay, but point being, if he paused for enough
of a moment in time and he took the שטר shtar? *shtar*,
then it's considered like he had a רצון *ratzon* to be קונה
koneh *koneh* it. And the fact that he's yelling now means he
changed his mind. So if you want to go ahead and give
it away, fine, go ahead and give it away. But it doesn't
prevent you from owning it. You right now own it. And if
you want to divest yourself of it, you're going to have to
go ahead and give it away. Well, I don't know how obvious
it is. Certainly, depending on the amount of time it took you
to start yelling, you might say it's like גלויי מילתא *gilluy milta*.
We assume your initial silence maybe was just trying to, you know,
process the information. Okay, so the חדוש *chiddush* is we don't say
that the צווח *tzoveiach* in the end means that shows that you
never wanted it. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, *amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*.
Is it the element of what obligations might come with it that
might be considered...
Well, that's an excellent point, and we're going to get to that
in a minute, right? You know, so you know, maybe מרבה נכסים
מרבה דאגה *marbeh nechasim marbeh da'aga*, now I'm going to have to,
you know, now who knows, you know, people might, you know, now
I'm a target for people. If you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam
*Rashbam*, the first line of the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*, maybe some more
of a moral point. If you look at the first line of
the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* here, כאן בצווח מעיקרא *kan b'tzoveiach meikara*, מתחילה
כשמסר לו זה השטר *metchila k'shemasar lo zeh hashtar*, he started yelling,
הלכך לא קנה *hilkach lo kana*, שאין מזכין לאדם בעל כרחו *she'ein
mazkin l'adam ba'al karcho*, you can't force somebody to get something against
his will. דכפו ליה דכתיב *d'chaful lo dich'tiv*, שונא מתנות יחיה sonei
matanot yichyeh, *sonei matanot yichyeh*. It's,
now why don't you say, you know, like זכין לאדם שלא בפניו
zachin leadam shelo befanav. *zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav*? First of all, it's
not שלא בפניו shelo befanav. *shelo b'fanav*, okay? But I, we can
talk about that case as well, case about שלא בפניו *shelo b'fanav*.
But anyway, but he also gives a reason why Michael wouldn't want
it, you know, שונא מתנות יחיה *sonei matanot yichyeh*. It's, you know,
like, you know, I, thank you, you know, I don't like to
live on the, who was it, Blanche DuBois, the kindness of others.
I don't like to live off of the kindness of others. I
like to make my own way through life, okay? You know, obviously
sometimes ברוך השם *Baruch Hashem* we need other people's support, but I
don't like taking gifts. Okay, so there could be a moral point,
there could be a point about the fear about, you know, about
like, does it put you as a target? What are your responsibilities
once you have more property? Whatever the reason is, you're entitled to
say no. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* points us to an interesting
point, because as a general rule, הלכה halacha, *halacha* assumes that to
gift you something is a benefit for you. זכין לאדם שלא בפניו
zachin leadam shelo befanav, *zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav*. So if Michael isn't
around and I go to Gloria and I say, 'Gloria, here, take,
you know, you know, be... you know, give me your handkerchief and
whatever, and by me taking your handkerchief you'll be קונה koneh. *koneh*
my nice new car for Michael.' Okay, the assumption is that she
can do that and Michael is קונה koneh *koneh* it from that
second, because the assumption is that that's to somebody's benefit to have
some piece of property. We'll get to that, okay? So that's how
normally זכין zachin. work. Or if I have to make an עירוב,
eruv, not an עירוב eruv with a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, but
an עירוב eruv that everybody jointly owns like some bread or מצה
matzah or whatever so that we can all carry, I can say,
Michael, here, be קונה koneh this box of מצה matzah on behalf
of everybody in the town, and now everybody owns a little portion
in this box of מצה matzah so we have an עירוב. eruv.
Why can you—somebody say—why could he do that for me? I didn't
appoint him as my שליח. shaliach. No, we assume זכין לאדם שלא
בפניו. zachin leadam shelo befanav. That you can merit somebody even not
in their presence, and that for somebody to take possession of something,
to own something, would be a benefit to them, and therefore you
can do it without asking them and you're seen to be operating
on their behalf. However, because it is just a presumption of operating
on their behalf, and a presumption of being for that benefit, if
somebody was to come along—if after I, you know, Gloria was קונה
koneh my car for Michael, Michael came along and he said, like,
oh my god, I can't keep up those insurance payments, or שונא
מתנות יחיה, or I don't know now Dov is going to ask
me to give him my car, or whatever Michael says, I never—I
don't want it. So then we say, oh, so retroactively he never
owned it. The only reason it worked when Gloria did it on
his behalf was a presumption that it was for his benefit. If
he as soon as he finds out objects, then we see that
it wasn't—that he didn't want it and it wasn't for his benefit
and it didn't take place.
Yes, you're telling me, right? You can't take a ride in your
car and then
say—well, that would be like made—that's שתק מעיקרא ולבסוף צוח. shatek meikara
ulesof tzavach. That would be like this. So the גמרא's Gemara scenario
could have been not that I handed the שטר shtar to Michael
and it took him a minute to stop yelling or to start,
you know, whatever, because then you start raising questions: why did he
take the שטר shtar in the first place? What was the context
he thought I was giving him the שטר shtar in? An easier
scenario for the exact same פסק psak of the גמרא Gemara was
that I was מקנה makne it to him through a third party,
and then as soon as he found out, did he start yelling
the minute he found out or did he only start yelling like
a few minutes later? Okay,
so, so the גמרא Gemara isn't clear what that case is. The
רשב"ם Rashbam says I gave him the שטר, shtar, but then again,
it's just a little stranger. So why did he take the שטר?
shtar. What did he think he was taking? Okay, you could make
up a scenario. But it is the same thing if you did
it through a third
party: זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin leadam shelo befanav, but when the
person finds out, they're in a position to object. By the way,
I should mention that this actually plays out in a very important
area of הלכה, Halacha which is גירות. geirus. A גר קטן. ger
katan. Why can a בית דין—what beis din authorizes a בית דין
beis din to convert a minor? So the principle—meaning he's not an
adult to make that decision. Maybe he wouldn't want to become Jewish.
Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says—so okay, if their parents—so if there's a parent, a
biological parent who's whatever then you have to say why are they
not Jewish etc. So let's say it's a biological father and you
know, the father is Jewish, the mother isn't Jewish, so then it
could be that the father supplies the דעת daat and that could
be that then you don't operate on the principle of זכין. But
let's say somebody, you know, basically goes ahead and adopts a child
or there's a foundling child, okay? Who's making the decision on behalf
of the child to convert him? So the גמרא Gemara says the
בית דין. beis din. Why? Because זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. Because the
child is not present, like he's not an adult yet, he's not—doesn't
have the mind, the will, the recognized will. So they do it
on the presumption that somebody would rather be Jewish than not Jewish,
which then the גמרא Gemara questions. Okay, but anyway, but then the
גמרא gemara, says, ah, but when he gets to be an adult,
he has a right to be מוחה, mocheh, because then what's—what's his
identity to be מוחה? mocheh? Because he could say, you only converted
me because you assumed I wanted, you were assumed to be operating
on my behalf. Now that I'm an adult and I have reached
the age of majority and I can make decisions for myself, I
am telling you it is not to my benefit. And then the
גירות geirus goes away. So it's actually a very interesting case when
you have cases of adopted children or whatever,
the rabbi will often like meet with them before their בר ובת
מצוה Bar and Bat Mitzvah and say like—like, you know, so—so you
know, do—so you know, do you still want to be Jewish? So
hopefully if you've raised them right the answer is yes. Anyway, it's—and
then the question about שתק מעיקרא ולבסוף צוח shatek meikara ulesof tzavach
is interesting because some say that the very fact that the kid
continues to practice Jewishly after their בר או בת מצוה Bar או
Bat Mitzvah is itself an implicit acceptance. And then if they were
to then say something afterwards, so, you know, so then it's too
late. They've already implicitly said they were okay with it. Anyway, it
becomes very interesting. So all of that is based on these issues
about זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, when you then find out or become
an adult or whatever, you could be מוחה, mocheh, and what happens
if first you're silent and then you're מוחה? mocheh? Okay, שתק מעיקרא
ולבסוף צוח. shatek meikara ulesof tzavach. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, זיכו
לו על ידי אחר ושתק ולבסוף צוח, ziku lo al yedei acher
veshatek ulesof tzavach, באנו למחלוקת של רבן גמליאל ורבנן. banu lemachloket shel
Rabban Gamliel verabanan. If you did it through another party, which is
sort of like what we were talking about, but the example I
was giving was you did it through another party שלא בפניו. This
is going to be a case that I gave it to Gloria
to be—Gloria, I took Gloria's handkerchief to be מקנה my car to
Michael and Michael was standing right there. Give it to me? I
don't know. But anyway, okay, because then maybe— It makes it a
little bit more, why I chose that I don't know, okay, but
it makes it a little bit more interesting in terms of gauging
your reaction. Okay, so he says, in that case, באנו למחלוקת רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל ורבנן. Banu L'machlokes Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel v'Rabbanan. It's
a debate between Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel and the Rabbanan. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a
Braisa: הכותב נכסיו לאחר, you wrote your property over to somebody else,
והיו בהן עבדים. v'hayu bahen avadim. Okay, you wrote your property over
to somebody else and here's the issue that David, you were raising
about your
responsibility—there were slaves in the property. Somebody's going to have to feed
the slaves and house the slaves.
ואמר הלה, the person who received it—maybe here would be a scenario
also where you could give a guy a שטר Shtar and first
they accept the שטר Shtar and then they want to back out—is
that the שטר shtar said all my property. So I was happy
to take all your property. Then I start looking at a detailed
list and I realize, wait a minute, that means that I'm also
taking the slaves. Whoa, I didn't agree to that.
Exactly מגילת רות, Megillat Ruth, right? Because that's the גואל. Goel.
Oh yeah, first he says yes, whoa, I gotta take רות? Ruth?
Hold on. So okay. So והיו בהן עבדים, v'hayu bahen avadim, אמר
הלה, amar hala, 'אי אפשי בהן, no, I don't want them.'
You can't do a partial
retraction?
Correct.
Meaning—correct. אם היה רב שני כהן—now Im haya rav sheini Kohen let's
say Michael here was a כהן—הרי אלו אוכלין בתרומה, too late. You
already took the שטר, shtar. they're yours. And here's a halachic consequence,
you know, like even for ritual matters, not just דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos matters. They're now the slaves of a כהן Kohen and they
can eat תרומה terumah and it's too late. Sorry that you don't
want them anymore. You already took the שטר. shtar רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, כיון שאמר הלה אי אפשי
בהן, keivan she-amar hala iy efshi ba-hen, as soon as Michael said
'I don't want them', כבר זכו בהן יורשים. kvar zachu ba-hen yorshim.
So then it is no longer the—you know, Michael's, the קנין did
not work, and if the giver died, because that would be an
example why you're writing away your property is because you're on your
deathbed or whatever. So in a scenario where the one who gave
it has died, they would go to his heirs, meaning the קנין
did not take effect. I want to just pause for a second
and say this long תוספות Tosafos and the רשב"ם Rashbam discuss a
possible opinion, which is is that they become הפקר. hefker. That I
tried to give it to Michael, he refused it, it stopped being
mine, it never became his, and they exist in this no-man's-land and
they're הפקר hefker and anybody can take them. So תוספות Tosafos goes
at great length to argue that nobody really says that, because the
only reason I gave it to Michael, the only reason I divested
myself of it, was because I wanted him to have it. I
wasn't like putting it into some zone called הפקר hefker and letting
him take it from הפקר. hefker. I was giving it to him.
If that did not complete, then nothing happened. Okay, so anyway, and
that's certainly the simple sense here, כבר זכו בהן יורשים. kvar zachu
ba-hen yorshim. Okay. ובעינן בהו, v'bayinan ba-hu, and we asked on this:
ותנא קמא אפילו עומד וצווח? v'tanna kamma afilu omed v'tzoveach? You mean
to tell me the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would say even if
Michael was yelling and screaming as soon as he found out there
were עבדים, avadim, right, as soon as he became aware of it,
he started yelling and screaming, and you would say that he still
קונה anyway? Okay, so אמר רבא ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, amar Rava v'isima
Rabbi Yochanan, בצווח
מעיקרו דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא קני. b'tzoveach me'ikaro d'kulei alma lo
pligi d'lo kani. If he started yelling from the outset, everybody agrees
he did not take possession. Now, we said that there was
an—לא פליגי דקני, lo pligi d'kani, he takes possession. כי פליגי, ki
pligi, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. דלא קני. d'lo kani. שתק
ולבסוף צווח, shasok u'l'vasof tzovach, if he was silent and then he
screamed, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דקני. d'kulei alma lo pligi d'kani. Everybody
agrees that was a later attraction and he is קונה. Now, we
actually were just describing a more complicated scenario, that he was quiet
because before and then he realized what the specifics were. Would that
be considered שתק ולבסוף צווח shasok u'l'vasof tzovach or would that be
considered צווח מעיקרו? tzoveach me'ikaro? It's not exactly clear. I would put
it in the צווח מעיקרו—as tzoveach me'ikaro soon as you became aware,
you started screaming. But anyway, okay, but if if you first were
silent presumably when it was significant, when maybe you were aware, and
then you started screaming, then okay, too late. כי פליגי, ki pligi,
now the Gemara says like this: כי פליגי שזיכה לו על ידי
אחר ושתק ולבסוף צווח. ki pligi she-zikah lo al yedei acher v'shasok
u'l'vasof tzovach. Okay, that it was through a third party and you
were silent and then you screamed. דתנא קמא סבר מדשתק קנהו. de-Tanna
Kamma savar mi-deshashok kannehu. Since you were initially silent, you're קונה it.
והאי דקא צווח מהדר הוא דקא הדר ביה. v'hai d'ka tzovach mahadar
hu d'ka hadar beih. And why do you now
scream? Now you're changing your mind. Too late. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל
סבר הוכיח סופו על תחילתו. v'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar hochich sofo
al techilaso. No, the fact that you're screaming now makes it clear
that you never wanted it. So why is it different when it's
through a third party than when it's you yourself? Okay, because והאי
דלא צווח עד השתא, v'hai d'lo tzovach ad hashta, so because the
reason he didn't start screaming until now was דסבר כי לא מטי
לידי מאי אצווח? d'savar ki lo mati l'yadi mai atzvach? Until I
have to take possession of it, what, I should start screaming? Because
I saw Gloria and Dove doing some weird thing with a handkerchief
and they were whatever—like until I start really feeling that it's mine,
or you know sort of even if I'm not going to start
screaming. So that's why the על ידי אחר al yedei acher sort
of matters. Now again, the רשב"ם Rashbam says it was even in
Michael's presence. Okay, that's why—so there's really are three scenarios, right? One
scenario is I do it with Gloria in a different room and
then I come and I tell Michael about it, right? So, you
know, so in that type of a case—so that's like—that's
the—you could say that's the case of the Gemara, but that's not
what the רשב"ם Rashbam says. The רשב"ם Rashbam says the case of
the Gemara is we're doing it in Michael's presence. Okay. So Michael
sees, and he sees and he's silent. So that you could reasonably
understand that the fact that he sees and he's silent is translated
as he's okay with it. But the other interpretation is no, like
it has he's not really yet owning the fact that this relates
to him. Right, you know, it's not really yet, so because he
isn't directly involved yet in what has happened, he his silence is
not yet meaningful. Yeah.
So according to the פירוש peirush he says he's not קונה before
he starts yelling and protesting, the עבדים avadim receiving and eating תרומה
terumah materials, and as soon as he screams he has to stop
eating like that moment.
Right. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. Okay, so you could again so so it
is interesting to think as I said about like a three like
there's a couple of, you know, as we sort of, you know,
there's a couple of like gray zones here. Right, one gray zone
is that Michael accepts it and then he becomes aware of the
specifics. Is that שתק מתחילה shatak mitchila or is that צווח מתחילה
tzavach mitchila
because what is the time that's significant? You could understand a case
where we did it in a different room and then...
not that I know of. Yeah, sorry. We should have one in
the בית מדרש. beit midrash. Anyway, so, right, so, right, anyway you
could imagine a case where like I said where it's like in
a different room and then maybe the coming in and informing Michael
of it, maybe that's,
maybe the coming in informing Michael of it is the is the
like the you know that would be just like him doing the
קנין. You've now been informed, we came into the room we told
you what you did you've been informed. This is just like you
did the קנין yourself. But seeing it and not reacting as opposed
to being informed about it, right that might be that's this space
where we have this type of a debate. Okay, yes.
So the הדר ביה hadar beih is the thing that even after
you were קונה עבדים avadim then you can undo it?
No, means you're trying to undo it but you're not succeeding. Exactly,
you're and you're not succeeding. That's exactly שתק ולבסוף צווח shatak u'levasof
tzavach according to this opinion is not effective. Okay, תנו רבנן tanu
rabanan we taught שכיב מרע שאמר תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני. shachiv meira
she'amar tenu matayim zuz leploni. Now back to שכיב מרע. shachiv meira.
Now we'll sort of end with some of these digressions as it
were, although this might not have been a digression because, you know,
the fact that it used the phrase יורשים yorshim seems to be
that the גמרא gemara is also imagining that the person who's doing
this is on the deathbed. And you could certainly imagine that, somebody
bequeaths things on a deathbed and what happens if one of the
recipients says no, I refuse? I don't want to take it. Okay?
So we're back anyway we're moving back into שכיב מרע shachiv meira
world and certainly now we're back into שכיב מרע shachiv meira world.
Did we discuss whether it becomes ownerless or not?
Yeah, I mean I said that the רשב"ם Rashbam suggests that there's
a possibility it did, but תוספות Tosafot really very strongly rejects that.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, שכיב מרע שאמר תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני, shachiv
meira she'amar tenu matayim zuz leploni, if a שכיב מרע shachiv meira
says give 200 dollars to so-and-so, ושלש מאות לפלוני, v'shalosh me'ot leploni,
200 to Sarah, 300 to Rivka, וארבע מאות לפלוני v'arba me'ot leploni
and 400 to Leah. Okay? So אין אומרים כל הקודם בשטר זוכה.
ein omrim kol hakodem b'shtar zocheh. Now it turns out so if
you were counting that's 900 dollars. Okay? Now let's say he only
had 700 dollars. All right? So do you distribute the money in
the order in which he listed the gifts? All right? So you
don't say that. Right? Because just because he listed in an order,
I mean you have to list in an order, you can't say
everything at once. So we don't assume that the order by itself
is significant. And you could have also said the opposite, maybe the
person he gave the most amount of money to was the person
he loved the most or cared about the most and maybe we
should start with that person. So you don't do by the order,
you don't do by the amount. In a normal case you take
the total assets, you look at how he distributed it, if the
total amount is less than the way he distributed it, you divide
the assets proportionally. Okay? So in this case it was four, three
and two, if he didn't have 900 dollars but he had 90
dollars, you would give 40, 30 and 20 rather than 400, 300
and 200. All right? So order doesn't matter and amount doesn't matter,
if there's less assets you divide it proportionally. אין אומרים ein omrim
you don't say
what לפיכך יצא עליו שטר חוב. lefikach yatza alav shtar chov. Let's
say therefore before he died, it would have to be before he
died because of the issue of חיבור chibur I don't want to
get into, anyway before he died what you had he did have
900 dollars but before he died came along a creditor that we
had all forgotten about and seized, you know, 500 of those dollars.
So now he so actually the statement made sense when he had
given it but now he died and there's only 400 dollars left
in the estate, so you divide it proportionally. Okay? So גובה מכולם,
goveh mikulam, that money gets taken effectively from everybody and meaning the
other way to say it is what is left is divided proportionally
based on the amount he intended to give.
Now אבל aval that's in a normal case.
אבל aval if he said תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני. tenu matayim zuz
leploni. 400 זוז zuz to Leah. So the words after mean if
there's any money's left in the estate, then they should go next
to that person, and if there's still anything left it should go
next to that person. So in that case he clearly has indicated
the order in which he wants the stuff distributed. Okay, so therefore
in that case אומרים כל הקודם בשטר זוכה, omrim kol hakodem bashtar
zocheh, the first it goes in the order in which they appear.
ולפיכך יצא עליו שטר חוב, velifichach yatza alav shtar chov, if somebody
came, a creditor came in and took the money from the estate
before he died and now there's less than he had intended, גובה
מן האחרון, gove min ha'acharon, it gets taken away from the last
person effectively, right, the last person last in first out, you know,
the last person on that list loses
first, אין לו גובה משלפניו, ein lo gove mishelifanav, if that wasn't
enough to pay the creditor you get to the second to last
person, אין לו גובה משלפני פניו, ein lo gove mishelifne fanav, and
only after those two have lost out and there's still not enough
you go to the first person. Now the simple sense of this
גמרא, gemara I've been saying the creditor comes before he dies. The
simple scenario of the גמרא gemara doesn't sound that way. It sounds
like the money was distributed to Sarah, Rifka, and Rachel, the creditor
came and he has to now start taking land away from them
in which order does he take it away? The problem with saying
it that way is that if what we gave to them was
money, cash, then the creditor would not have right to take the
cash away. After the guy dies, the creditor only has right to
take away land. So either you have to say the גמרא gemara
means the creditor came before he died, or you have to say
200, 300, 400 זוז zuz don't mean actual cash, it means that
amount of land. So if he gave a certain amount, you know,
that amount of land to Sarah and that amount of land to
Rachel and that amount of land to Leah, and then he died
and the creditor came, the first person he would take use his
have to use his liens against would be first like you know
he'd have to go in the reverse order if the person said
אחריו, acharav, because the word אחריו acharav is then interpreted to mean
like I want only if there is money left over in the
estate do I then want it to go next to that person
and then next to that person. I know, I'm just saying, to
explain when the creditor came. Either he came after death and there
was land, or he came before death and we're talking about cash.
If he had language in the כתובה ketubah of 200 זוז, zuz,
therefore I should understand primarily as real estate?
No, no no no. I mean, it's money with- it's money with
liens on real estate. Right. No, you have to- no, meaning that's
why either the- the גמרא gemara isn't פשט pshat in one way.
Either the זוז zuz here does not mean זוז, zuz, it means
land with- of this value, or when it says the creditor came
it meant the creditor came before he died. But you can't have
both of them combined. Yeah.
Did you mention at some point that in the גאונים gaonim period
that they accepted cash as well as?
Yes, in the- yes, so post the גאונים תקנה, gaonim takana, then
this could ap- then the גמרא gemara could be like it's like
the פשט, pshat, because after the גאונים תקנה, gaonim takana, a creditor
could collect from the cash of the estate. That is correct. Okay,
so now it goes like this.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we taught. שכיב מרע shchiv mera שאמר, she'amar,
תנו מאתיים זוז לפלוני בני בכורי כראוי לו, tnu masayim zuz leploni
beni bechori karaui lo, give 200 זוז zuz to Ploni my firstborn
son as is fit for him. So the question is why did
you mention your firstborn son? Does that mean the 200 זוז zuz
is your assigning of his חלק בכורה? chelek bechora? Like, anyway, you're
not allowed to play with the חלק בכורה, chelek bechora, לא יוכל
לבכר lo yuchal levaker anyway, so how are we supposed to read
this? Okay, so it says נוטלן ונוטל בכורתו. notlan venotel bechorato. This
has no impact on the חלק בכורה, chelek bechora, he gets the
200 זוז, zuz, and why he said my firstborn son כראוי לו
karaui lo who knows? I mean, we'll see in a minute. Okay,
but it means in addition to what he's entitled to in terms
of his regular inheritance. However, here's the real חידוש. chidush. אם אמר
im amar בבכורתו, bevechorato, let him take 200 זוז zuz as his
בכורה bechora inheritance. So then now of course I as the father
cannot go ahead and take away his בכורה bechora inheritance, so what's
the meaning of my saying 200 זוז zuz in his inheritance? So
it means he can choose. Would he prefer the 200 זוז zuz
as-
instead of the, you know, what in inheritance חלק chelek would normally
come out to be. So ידו על העליונה, yado al ha'elyona, he
has the choice. רצה נוטלן, ratza notlan, if he wants he can
take the 200 זוז, zuz, רצה נוטל בכורתו, ratza notel bechorato, he
could say no, forget the 200 זוז, zuz, I'm just going to
take my my normal double portion. Question with all these things is
like what's the moment in time when he makes- when that choice
becomes final, you know? But anyway, all right, but then the father
basically gave him an option, essentially said to you if you're willing
to waive your חלק בכורה, chelek bechora, I will therefore give you
200 זוז zuz from the estate. So the father isn't stripping him
of it, he's effectively giving him an option. Okay, now, ובשכיב מרע
שאמר ubeshchiv mera she'amar similarly if a שכיב מרע shchiv mera says,
תנו מאתיים זוז לפלונית אשתי, tnu masayim zuz leplonit ishti, give 200
זוז zuz to Sarah my wife, כראוי לה, keraui lah, as fit
for her. Now of course 200 זוז zuz as Rabbi Dov mentioned
before is just standard כתובה ketubah payment. So maybe he's just there
trying to make sure that his wife gets paid. paid her כתובה,
ketubah, like everybody, you know, maybe he's telling people, hey, I haven't
prepaid the כתובה, ketubah, make sure you're on top of making sure
my wife gets her כתובה. ketubah. Okay, נוטלם ונוטלת כתובתה. notlam venotelet
ketubatah. So even though he said "my wife", and even though he
said כראוי לה keraui la as fit to her, and you might
think כראוי לה keraui la exactly means in payment for what she
is owed as כתובה ketubah payment, the חידוש chiddush is that no,
as long as he's not, we're not going to read it that
way. The same point by the בכור, bechor, we're not going to
read כראוי keraui instead of something he's owed or in payment of
something he's owed, we're going to read it just as like in
addition to everything they're entitled to, not as payment for what they're
entitled to, but in addition to what they're entitled to. So in
addition to what she's entitled to, give her two hundred זוז. zuz.
נוטלם ונוטלת כתובתה. notlam venotelet ketubatah. אם אמר בכתובתה, im amar biketubatah,
if he's more explicit and he says give her the two hundred
זוז zuz as payment of her
כתובה, ketubah, ידה על העליונה, yadah al haelyonah, she has her choice.
רצתה נוטלתן, ratztah notletan, if she wants she can take the two
hundred זוז, zuz, רצתה נוטלת כתובתה, ratztah notlet ketubatah, she can take
the כתובה. ketubah. So someone will say, "Oh, the כתובה ketubah is
two hundred זוז." zuz. I don't know, maybe she was an אלמנה
almanah when she got married, maybe it was only one hundred זוז,
zuz, maybe he had prepaid some of the כתובה, ketubah, okay, maybe
whatever, exactly, anyway. So if you say בכתובתה, biketubatah, then it means
that you are, you know, he doesn't have a right to take
away any of her rights, but he can say let this be
her כתובה ketubah payment, and she can choose whether to accept that
as her כתובה ketubah payment or accept what her כתובה ketubah payment
officially was.
Why would she choose her כתובה ketubah if she was an אלמנה
almanah and the כתובה ketubah was less than the two hundred זוז?
zuz?
Why would she opt for that? Because the כתובה ketubah of, that's
also an interesting question of what it means בכתובתה, biketubatah, because the
כתובה ketubah also includes not only the flat amount, but it also
includes the תוספת tosefet and it includes the, what do you call
it, the נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel that she brought in.
So sometimes if she doesn't choose the כתובה, ketubah, she could lose
her נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel.
If she does, right, so that's not clear whether the
בכתובתה biketubatah mean, I understand, but she could also, she could waive
it. It's not clear whether the word בכתובתה biketubatah here means in
the base כתובה ketובה payment or in the entire thing that she
takes out of the כתובה. ketubah. But it's still a good question
because you normally, the whole point of נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon
barzel is that their value is protected. So you actually write their
value in the כתובה. ketובה. It doesn't require any new assessing of
value. That's why we say, you know, דהא כל קיבל עליו החתן
במאה זקוקים כסף צרוף deha kol kibel alav hachatan bemeah zekukim kesef
tzaruf means that this is what he is assessing the value of
the property that she is bringing in. So it's hard to imagine
like why, where would be the case of, that there would be
a logic to take, since the dollar values are pretty well spelled
out. I don't know, again maybe the point is also, I'm trying
to think, I'd have to think about why there would be, yes.
If she chose the property instead of the כתובה, ketובה, would that
still count as her having been given the כתובה ketובה in terms
of like her being able to still live on the estate?
Yeah, no, because then she is, like it would be like taking
the lump sum כתובה. ketובה. Look, in the case of two hundred
זוז, zuz, I can't see a good scenario, but I could see
a scenario if he said let her take my nice, you know,
Corvette for her payment of her כתובה, ketובה, and then she can
decide, would she rather, you know, how much is that Corvette worth
in terms of its actual resale value, sentimental value, whatever, you know?
So there, but when she says two hundred זוז, zuz, it's all
dollar amounts, I can't think of a good scenario. Okay. ושכיב מרע
שאמר, veshechiv mera sheamar, now ושכיב מרע shechiv mera says, תנו מאתיים
זוז לפלוני בעל חובי כראוי לו, tnu matayim zuz leploni baal chovi
keraui lo, give two hundred זוז zuz to ראובן Reuven there, my
creditor, as is fit for him. נוטלן ונוטל חובו. notlan venotel hovo.
Like we're going to say, like we said before, as long as
you don't say let it be in payment of the debt, we
read it as in addition to what I owe him. Okay, ואם
אמר בחובו, veim amar behovo, in payment of the debt, נוטלן בחובו,
notlan behovo, then he gets it in the debt. Now a couple
of people reacted to this, like,
it's one thing, your son, your wife, you might want to give
something extra, but somebody else who's not a family member, who you
identify as your creditor. It didn't say if you say it about
your next-door neighbor who happens to be your creditor. This is a
person that you've identified as your banker and as your creditor. How
could we not read כראוי לו keraui lo meaning in payment of
the debt? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara reacts as well. So the
גמרא Gemara says, משום דאמר כראוי לו נוטלן ונוטל חובו? mishum deamar
keraui lo notlan venotel hovo? Just because he said the words כראוי
לו, keraui lo, he gets it in addition to his debt? Like
כראוי לו keraui lo even maybe itself should even mean in payment
of the debt. ודילמא כראוי בחובו קאמר, vedilma keraui behovo kaamar, as
is he deserves because of payment of the debt. Now you could
have said that about the wife and the בכור bechor as well,
okay, but, you know, but nevertheless there they have a relationship, what?
You're not really viewing them, yeah,
the wife has a debt, but whatever, but the relationship is fundamentally
different. Here, like, of course, like, why should we all of a
sudden assume you're giving a gift to your creditor? אמר רב נחמן
אמר לי הונא המני רבי עקיבא היא, amar Rav Nachman amar li
Huna hamani Rabbi Akiva hi, this is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דדייק
לישנא יתירא, dedayek lishna yetira, who... that he infers from the extra
language. דתנן. de'tnan. Where do you see this? So let's first see
the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and then we'll apply it. Okay. ולא
את הבור ולא את הדות. ve'lo et ha'bor ve'lo et ha'dut. Okay,
you might remember this, right? Whether מוכר בעין רעה מוכר, מוכר בעין
יפה מוכר. mocher be'ayin ra'ah mocher, mocher be'ayin yafah mocher. I sell
Michael my entire house, okay, and he gets the house, but he
does not get the cistern, which maybe as we discussed at the
time, is even inside the home itself. Okay, no, that's a cistern,
that's not the home. You get the home, you don't get the
plumbing. Okay, anyway, ולא את הבור ולא את הדות. ve'lo et ha'bor
ve'lo et ha'dut. Okay. אף על פי שכתב לו עומקא ורומא, af
al pi she'katav lo umka ve'ruma, even though I write that Michael,
you have the height and the you know, you have the house,
its height and
its depth, right, you get everything that's called house, but the cistern
is not the house and you don't get that. Okay, so that's
the position. וצריך ליקח לו דרך דברי רבי עקיבא. ve'tzarich likach lo
derech divrei Rabbi Akiva. So Rabbi Akiva says, okay, שכוח, shkoach, טוב.
You still retain the cistern in the house, but Michael doesn't have
to let you in his house. If you want to go in
and out, you have to buy you know, get right of way
from Michael. וחכמים אומרים, ve'Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say אין צריך
ליקח לו דרך. ein tzarich likach lo derech. No, if you same
way you retain for yourself the well, the cistern, you retain for
yourself
ingress and right to get access to the well. Okay, so that
the גמרא Gemara frames as, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, מוכר
בעין יפה מוכר. mocher be'ayin yafah mocher. I gave Michael maximal, at
least maximal what's defined as the house, the well I keep. וחכמים
אומרים ve'Chachamim omrim בעין רעה מוכר. be'ayin ra'ah mocher. No, I try
to hold on to as much as possible, and if I'm keeping
the well for myself, I'm going to keep access to the well
for myself as well. Okay, now, here comes the line that's relevant
for us. ומודה רבי עקיבא בזמן שאמר לו חוץ מאלו. u'modeh Rabbi
Akiva bizman she'amar lo chutz me'eilu. However, let's say I say, Michael,
I am selling you my house, but except I am not selling
you my well and my cistern. Now, I didn't have to say
that because that was automatically excluded anyway. So if I went out
of my way to say that, that extra language means I want
to hold on to something more. Okay, so since I said that,
חוץ מאלו, chutz me'eilu, שאין צריך ליקח לו דרך. she'ein tzarich likach
lo derech. In that case I am holding on to right of
access, and I don't have to purchase it from Michael. Okay, now,
אלמא, alma, so you see, כיון דלא צריך וקאמר, keivan d'lo tzarich
ve'ka'amar, since you didn't have to say those words, and you said
those extra words, except for the well, because that was implicit, לטפויי
מילתא קאתא, le'tifuyei milta ka'ata, you're coming to add, you know, to
give yourself extra. We're going to interpret those words and say you're
giving yourself extra, since you're saying I'm holding on to X. You
already were holding on to X, it means even more than X.
In other words, טפי. tfei. טפי. tfei.
Now, the רשב"ם Rashbam points out, you know, that it's not like
the חכמים Chachamim disagree with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva about this. Presumably
the חכמים Chachamim would also agree that if you use an extra
language, you're holding on to more. It's just they didn't need that.
They already were giving the guy X. But for רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that didn't give the guy access, he said, oh, if you
use extra language, then you will get access. But presumably this is
a principle that everybody holds of, that if you use extra language,
we assume you're trying to hold on to something extra. Okay, so
the point being, had I just said, give my בעל חוב ba'al
chov 200 זוז, zuz, of course it would have meant in payment
of the debt. So why did I say כראוי לו? ke'ra'uy lo?
Okay, now, again, that's funny because I hear that you said extra
words you didn't have to say, but how do the extra words
lead to the translation you've given them? Meaning if I am רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and I'm saying except for the well, so the
word except means I'm making sure I'm holding on to something, and
at least the access to the well is associated with the well.
So the extra words except for the well can be parsed as
except for the well and the access to the well because I
didn't have to say except for the well. But if I'm saying,
give my בעל חוב ba'al chov 200 זוז zuz and I would
have stopped there and it would have meant in payment, and instead
I said as is fit for him, why
as, so you could say as is fit for him, he's a
nice guy and therefore it's fit for me to give him a
present, maybe. But is it clear that as is fit for him
suggests, you know, giving him extra?
So the way I understand that possibility is if it's contextualized. Meaning,
this was a creditor who helped me get my business.
Yeah, but I don't think the גמרא Gemara is right, maybe
he made it happen, could be. But I don't think the גמרא
Gemara is limiting it to that. He's given me for the last
20 years because my business was. Yeah, I understand
what you're
saying, but I don't think the גמרא Gemara is limiting it to
that. The גמרא Gemara didn't say you look at the circumstances, and
if this is a guy who's been lording it over me for
the last 20 years, right, and right? The גמרא Gemara isn't distinguishing
those cases. I think the only difference is that in רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva case I'm saying חוץ. chutz. So in רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva case I'm saying I'm holding on to something. So any extra
language, whatever its semantic meaning, is going to be read as I'm
holding on to more than I normally would be holding on to.
Whereas when I'm saying, give it to him, and I'm giving, then
any extra language, again, regardless of whether semantically it really has that
meaning in it or not, any extra language means give him even
more. Okay, that seems to be what we're saying. So don't just
give him in payment of the debt. Give him in even more.
Yes.
In all these discussions about a deathbed bequest, is there any
consideration of state of mind when the person might be losing their
clarity on things?
Yeah, that's a really good question, like in general הלכה Halacha doesn't
deal enough, it does a little bit, it talks about when is
דעתו צלולה, da'ato tzelula, לא צלולה not tzelula and so on, but
you know nowadays we deal a lot more with issues of like
dementia and so on because people live a lot longer and there's
not enough development in early הלכה around those questions of dementia etcetera,
although there is some. Okay, but you're right, we will so there's
sometimes it's both כנוסו, kenuso, you check him אם הייתה דעתו צלולה
im hayesa da'ato tzelula and so on, but there's a presumption that
he is of right mind you know, so it's only special cases
that the גמרא Gemara starts worrying about. Okay, so let's anyway end
this so the גמרא Gemara, says הכא נמי hacha nami so so
חוץ מעלמא כיון דלא צריך וקאמר לטפויי מילתא קאתי, chutz me-alma kivon
delo tzarich ve-ka'amar litfuyei milta ka-ati, הכא נמי כיון דלא צריך וקאמר
לטפויי מילתא קאתי hacha nami kivon delo tzarich ve-ka'amar litfuyei milta ka-ati
is extra now. Now so we know that in the case of
the חכמים, chachamim, in the case of the בכור, bechor, if you
just said give 200 זוז, zuz, it would mean in payment of
the debt. If you say כראוי לו, kara-uy lo, it means you
know in addition. What about the case of the wife? If you
said give her 200 זוז zuz and you didn't say כראוי לה,
kara-uy lah, you just said give her 200 זוז, zuz, would it
mean as a gift or is it or would it mean in
payment of the כתובה? kesuvah? What about the בכור? bechor? You need
to say 200 זוז zuz in payment of כתובה kesuvah because you
owe it anyway, so then why would you say it? Meaning as
opposed to it being just from land? I don't know, what, I'm
not sure what hold on, I'm not sure what your question is,
one sec, one sec. So the point is though that we have
pointed we pointed out that the case of the creditor is one
in where we're just naturally more inclined to assume what you're doing
is paying off your debt. Okay? And then that works in the
end, what we're saying is that if you just say give him
200 זוז zuz without any extra language, it means paying off the
debt. If you use extra language, it means as a gift. Okay?
But what about the case by the wife? By the wife we
said if you say 200 זוז zuz בכתובתה be-kesuvatah payment, it's paying
off the כתובה kesuvah and then she can choose.
If you say 200 זוז zuz כראוי לה, kara-uy lah, that's extra
language and it means as a gift. What if you just said
200 זוז zuz without כראוי לה kara-uy lah and without בכתובתה? be-kesuvatah?
So there right,
if we thought that was an exact parallel of the case of
the creditor, we would say it's payment of the כתובה, kesuvah, right?
But maybe not because the relationship is different, right? So without any
words to indicate, by a creditor of course we assume it means
payment, but what do you do if it's a simple statement by
the wife of give her 200 זוז? zuz? Does it mean as
a gift or does it mean in payment of the כתובה? kesuvah?
Well right, the גמרא Gemara, isn't clear but by its association with
the creditor it suggests that I you we should read that as
payment of the כתובה. kesuvah. Okay? So if you take a look
at the רשב"ם Rashbam here he says if you look back at
the previous עמוד, the רשב"ם Rashbam, says, yeah, he says by the
בכור bechor one two three five lines down in the widest lines
of the רשב"ם Rashbam on קל"ח עמוד א' he says ואילו לא
הוה אמר כראוי לו ve-ilo hava amar kara-uy lo he just said
give him this amount, היה נוטל בבכורתו רצה בכורתו נוטל רצה מאתים
זוז נוטל, haya notel be-bechoraso ratzah bechoraso notel ratzah masayim zuz notel,
ידו על העליונה. yado al ha-elyona. And similarly by the wife he
says, does he say it by the wife? No, let's look four
lines from the bottom end of the line. ברם אם אמר תנו
מאתים זוז לפלוני בני סתמא Beram im amar tnu masayim zuz le-ploni
beni stama ולא אמר בבכורתו velo amar be-bechoraso let's say it wasn't
a בכור, bechor, give 200 זוז zuz to my son, ידו על
העליונה כדאמרינן לקמן yado al ha-elyona kid-amrinan lekaman ודילמא קראי בכור קאמר
משנה דרבי אלעזר לשנא דתורה. vedilma kerai bechor ka-amar mishna d'Rabbi Elazar
lishana d'Torah. So if he just said give 200 זוז zuz to
my son, then it wouldn't mean a gift in addition to his
inheritance. It would mean he can choose the 200 זוז zuz as
an inheritance. Okay? But we would not say it meant as a
gift. Okay? And say does he say it explicitly by the so
he doesn't say explicitly by the by the כתובה, kesuvah, but basically
the רשב"ם Rashbam assumes it's all the same. That even in a
case so now all of a sudden this is like a shocker
to me, right? All of a sudden we're talking about a מתנת
שכיב מרע. shachiv meira Here's a guy on his deathbed. He's he's
dividing up a million dollars worth of his estate, but the rest
he's leaving in his bank account or whatever. He's got multi-millions and
whatever and there he is and he's taking this million and he
says you know give 100,000 to my son ראובן Reuven and 200,000
to שמעון Shimon and whatever and he distributes whatever he does and
then he dies. Okay? But he only mentioned a million dollars and
there's still ten million in the bank. I would have assumed he
meant this is in this is like in addition to whatever you're
going to inherit of the leftover money, right? But according to this
גמרא, Gemara according to the simple reading and the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it means no, if you want to take that 100,000
dollars, you're you're giving up your in exchange for you know what
your normal חלק chelek would be as a child you know as
an heir. And the same if a guy says... I'm holding onto
the Ferrari for myself. Give my wife my Corvette. So you would
assume it means give her the Corvette and then she still has
her כתובה Ksuva payment, right? Give my son my stamp collection. Fine,
you wanted Johnny to have the stamp collection, he always loved doing
stamps with you. No, all of a sudden now we find out
that if he takes the stamp collection, he's given up his חלק
Chelek of the ירושה, Yerusha, right? Can he say, 'Wait a second,
I'm not giving up anything by doing this?' What? Can he say?
No, we're reading it as take it as your inheritance, take it
as your כתובה. Ksuva. And you might get the choice, but to
me that's like crazy, I gotta tell you. Like, it's one thing
with a creditor where the basic relationship is you owe him money,
that if you don't clarify, we assume it means in payment of
the debt, right? But in a basic case of your family, right,
I would assume that it would mean this is a gift and
whatever I'm not talking about would be divided based on the normal
rules of inheritance. Not according to Rabbi Akiva though, no? No, the
גמרא, Gemara it's according to the רשב"ם, it doesn't matter. Wait, wait,
why, why? If a בעל חוב, Baal Chov, if you don't say
כראוי לו, Karoy Lo, you assume it's payment of the debt. Right.
You have to say כראוי לו Karoy Lo to get the choice.
Right. So then I was thinking, I was following you and saying
to myself the same thing is true of the בכור Bechor and
the woman and the wife. No, no, if you say כראוי לו
Karoy Lo he doesn't get a choice, if you say כראוי לו
Karoy Lo he gets it in addition to the debt. Okay. And
if you don't say כראוי לו, Karoy Lo, it's payment of the
debt. So the רשב"ם says, if you give your son something and
you
don't say כראוי לו, Karoy Lo, it's in exchange for his חלק
Chelek of the ירושה. Yerusha.
And if you say give your wife something and you don't say
כראוי לו, Karoy Lo, it's instead of her כתובה Ksuva payment. It's
not logically parallel. I know it's not logically parallel, that's why I'm
pointing it out. Oh, so you were saying it was parallel and
problematic? No, it's not parallel. Why is he... what's compelling him to
say that? Because of the way the גמרא Gemara lines it up,
the גמרא Gemara puts all three cases together. If you say כראוי
לו Karoy Lo by your wife, it's then she has a choice.
If you say כראוי לו Karoy Lo by your... no, if you
say כראוי לו Karoy Lo by your wife, it's in addition to
her כתובה Ksuva payment. If you say כראוי לו Karoy Lo by
your בכור, Bechor, it's in addition. If you say כראוי לו Karoy
Lo by your בעל חוב, Baal Chov, it's in addition. Okay. And
then the גמרא Gemara says what if you didn't say כראוי לו
Karoy Lo by your בעל חוב? Baal Chov? It would be payment
of your debt. What if you didn't say כראוי לו Karoy Lo
by your wife? It's in payment of your כתובה. Ksuva. What if
you didn't say כראוי לו Karoy Lo by your בכור? Bechor? It's
in payment of the בכור חלק. Bechor Chelek. Now, they have the
choice, but it's still crazy. The guy's on his deathbed and he
said, 'Give my son my stamp collection and my wife my Corvette,'
and then he dies and there's a million dollars left in his
estate. And we say, 'Oh, if you want to take the stamp
collection, you're giving up your חלק Chelek in the estate.' Like, that's
crazy. Okay, so yes. Suppose all the sons, you know, give each
of my sons a hundred thousand dollars. Right. And then there's two
million dollars left. What happens to the two million dollars? Oh, that's
interesting. You're meaning according to this logic, they've all now given up
their right of the בכור. Bechor. Oh, that's a good question. So
if they've all given it up and then you have... yeah, that's
a really good question. I don't know the answer to that. What?
That's why I'm asking you. Yeah, I don't know what to say.
But the גמרא Gemara is not explicit... the גמרא Gemara is not
explicit about that conclusion. That's what the רשב"ם says. You understand why
he's saying it because of the parallel, but the גמרא Gemara isn't
explicit. And it's clear that the גמרא Gemara understands that the בעל
חוב Baal Chov is different because the גמרא Gemara only reacted to
the בעל חוב Baal Chov case. It didn't react to the other
cases, which, right, you saw how the גמרא Gemara. did that. Which
makes it clear that the גמרא Gemara... understands that by the בעל
חוב, Baal Chov, we're more ready to interpret something to be in
payment of the debt, whereas I think we would less be ready
to assume that in the case of the wife and the kids.
But yes. That's interesting because to me that's what's compelling the רשב"ם
is he wants to make the whole thing parallel. Right, which is
certainly a reasonable read of the גמרא. Gemara... But the Talmud itself
singled out the בעל חוב. Baal Chov. Exactly. Right. But it's not
clear why they do that from a literary perspective. תנו רבנן שכיב
מרע שאמר מנה יש לי אצל פלוני. Tanu Rabbanan Shchiv Mera she'amar
maneh yesh li etzel ploni. So a guy's on his deathbed and
he says, 'You all should be aware that I owe Jenna a
thousand dollars.' Okay? So, העדים כותבים. Ha'edim kotvim. Now, exactly. So, now,
here's the thing. He... oh wait, I think I read it wrong.
Wait. Does he say I owe him or she owes me? I
think it means she owes me. I'm sorry, I take that back.
She owes me. Now it's on your... Listen guys, I want you
to know... sorry... listen guys, I want you to know that Jenna
owes me a thousand dollars. Now, that's just my word against hers,
right? If I came to court and said that, you know, I
wouldn't be believed, but the reason I am telling the witnesses that
is... My kids should be aware of it, they should try to
like maybe get evidence, they should be reminded of it, like it's
important that I note that even though I don't have any evidence,
and I want that to be remembered, okay, that Jenna owes me
a thousand dollars. So what do these people, these witnesses who heard
this fact do? This, can they keep a record of that? So
it says העדים כותבין אף על פי שאין מכירין. Ha'edim kotvin af
al pi she'ein makirin. The witnesses can write that down. Dov told
us that Jenna owes him a thousand dollars, even though they have
no idea who Jenna is. More important than they don't know who
Jenna is, but they don't even they don't know what I'm saying
is true or not. Okay? They just know that I said it.
They're allowed to say Dov said. They don't write down Jenna owes
Dov a thousand dollars. For them we were in Dov's room and
he told us that Jenna owes him a thousand dollars. Okay. And
now, לפיכך כשהוא גובה צריך להביא ראיה דברי רבי מאיר. Lefikach keshehu
goveh tzarich lehavi ra'aya divrei Rabbi Meir. So therefore if now let's
say witness I want to use this document or let's not make
it me who's saying this somebody else is on their deathbed saying
this and then he dies and then the kids want to use
this document. So they bring this document to court. Look, this document
said that our
father said that Jenna owes him a thousand dollars. It's like okay,
that's very nice that your father
said that. If you want to collect it, go bring some evidence.
Okay? דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what Rabbi Meir said.
וחכמים אומרים אין כותבין אלא אם כן מכירין. Vechachamim omrim ein kotvin
ela im ken makirin. No. The witnesses were not allowed to write
it down unless they knew that it was true. Okay? Unless they
themselves maybe were there at the time when she borrowed the money
or something. So they can only write it down if they knew
that it was true. Once that's true, if they're writing it down,
they're writing it down actually means that they are testifying to that
fact. ולפיכך כשהוא גובה אין צריך להביא ראיה. Ulefikach keshehu goveh ein
tzarich lehavi ra'aya. So therefore now when the heir wants to collect,
having this document alone is enough. So that's a big question, right?
Implicitly, so when you see a document that says we were with
פלוני Ploni and he said that Jenna owes him a thousand dollars,
okay? Does that mean we're just telling you what we heard? We
are not making any claim to the truth of it? Okay? Or
are they actually saying that we are actually testifying that we actually
the facts that were claimed are actually true? Now the point being
I would say since this is really not evidence, right? And it's
just going to be there to like I don't know remind the
heirs and have them investigate or so on, then why should they
write it as עדים? Edim? Just write it down like as a
diary notation. You know what I mean? We heard so-and-so say. Don't
sign it. Don't write it as עדים. Edim. If you're going to
be writing it as עדים Edim and all it is is somebody's
claim, right? So I don't know. Like I can't see a case
where it's a where it's important to have that as testimony in
the court that this is what this guy claims on his deathbed.
Okay. So if it's being written in the context of עדות, Edus,
I would think that it more should be interpreted as a claim
to the veracity of the thing. But anyway, but that's the question.
What do we assume when a שטר shtar says we heard somebody
say X and it's written with the signatures of witnesses? Are they
just testifying to the fact that he said it or are they
actually testifying to the content of what was being said? Yes. But
it fits with our categorization of like what someone says on their
deathbed as being more true. Right. Right. Maybe. I mean the גמרא...
Gemara Right. סתם. Stam. Right. But the... Right, but then why am
I telling witnesses, why am I not telling my kid? Right. So
the... But you could go that way. We're going to see the
גמרא... Gemara What? Right. The גמרא Gemara is going to make an
analogy and the גמרא Gemara is not going to make that difference,
but I you definitely could could think about that. Now I just
want to make sure we get to the משנה. Mishnah. Let's keep
on going. Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Nachman
amar Rav Huna. הונא Huna told me that the debate in the
reverse, like the names were reversed. תני רבי מאיר אומר אין כותבין
וחכמים אומרים כותבין. Tana Rabbi Meir omer ein kotvin vechachamim omrim kotvin.
You do write. So okay, he's got the names, the positions reversed.
ואף רבי מאיר Ve'af Rabbi Meir who says you don't write because
we're because why do you not write because because people will because
you don't know if it's true and then a court will see
this and assume that it is true. Okay? אף רבי מאיר לא
אמר אלא משום בית דין טועין. Af Rabbi Meir lo amar ela
mishum beit din to'in. Now the reason Rabbi Meir doesn't want you
to write it is he says look, it's an interesting nuance, meaning
one way of saying it is you're only empowered to write if
you know the veracity of the claim. Okay, so don't write, you
don't know the veracity of the claim. Another point is no, you
really are empowered to write and say we're just testifying this is
what he's saying. And any בית דין Beit din that knows what
it's doing will understand that you did not testify to the veracity
of the claim, you just testified to what the guy said. So
in principle you should be maybe able to write it because you're
not saying Jenna owes him a thousand dollars, you're saying we heard
so-and-so say Jenna owes him. So really everybody agrees in principle go
ahead and write it and any בית דין Beit din will understand
that you're not claiming something about the facts themselves. But there's sometimes
there's some bad בתי דין Batei din out there that are a
little sloppy and don't pay attention and they see a שטר shtar,
with witnesses on it that says so-and-so said and they will assume
it means that it's true. Okay? So you understand the difference. One
is don't write it because the writing it is the claim. that
it's true, and therefore don't write it unless you know it's true.
The other is no, the writing it is not the claim that
it's true, but we have to not write it because there are
sloppy בתי דינים batte dinim out there that will misinterpret it. Okay,
so that's this version of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now it says
like this, אמר רב דימי מנהרדעא, Amar Rav Dimi mi-Nehardea, הלכתא, hilchata,
הלכתא אין חוששין לבית דין טועין. hilchata ein chosheshin le-veit din to'in.
We're not afraid of sloppy בתי דין. batte din. You can go
ahead and write the שטר shtar. that this is what this person
said, and the בית דין beit din will know it's what he
said, but there's no proof that it's true or not, and go
ahead and write the שטר. shtar ומאי שנא מדרבא? U-mai shna mi-deRava?
Now how is it different from רבא teaches? דאמר רבא, De-amar Rava,
אין חולצין אלא אם כן מכירין, ein choltzin ela im ken makirin,
that a בית... beit... you cannot do חליצה chalitzah in a בית
דין. beit din. Okay, somebody comes for you here, like you mentioned
רות Ruth before, בועז Boaz and רות Ruth come in front of
you to do חליצה, chalitzah, okay, and you said like, I don't
know that this guy is what's-his-name's brother. He's just telling us he's
his brother, I have no evidence that that's true. So I say,
he says, but I'm telling you I'm the brother, so do we
let him do חליצה chalitzah and then we'll figure we'll write it
down? This guy by the name of בועז Boaz blah blah blah
did חליצה chalitzah and then some other בית דין beit din can
figure out if he was the brother or not because he's about
to take a trip to China. So do we let them do
it without knowing if it really is effective or not? Because we
don't know if he's the brother. Okay, that's the question. So he
says no, you cannot do it unless you know that this guy
is the brother and this חליצה chalitzah works. Okay, ואין ממאנין, ve-ein
memanin, מיאון miun is if a girl was married under age by
her mother or brothers, father is dead, and then she refuses the
guy she was married to. אלא אם כן מכירין, ela im ken
makirin, unless you know that this is the girl and that this
is the husband. Okay, לפיכך, l-fichach, now, so you have to make
sure that you know, כותבין גט חליצה וגט מיאון ואף על פי
שאין מכירין. kotvin get chalitzah ve-get miun ve-af al pi she-ein makirin.
So therefore, here's the funny thing, if I know that a בית
דין beit din won't do it unless they know who the parties
are, so if I'm walking by a בית דין, beit din, me
and אלי Eli there were walking by a בית דין, beit din,
and we see a חליצה chalitzah going up and we know who
the parties are, we can go ahead and write down a שטר
shtar and basically say, you know, that so-and-so had a legitimate חליצה.
chalitzah. Why can we write it down that it was a legitimate
חליצה? chalitzah? Because we know that the בית דין beit din would
never have performed it unless they were certain that this was the
brother or brother-in-law. So we can actually write down שרה Sarah has
been permitted על ידי חליצה, al yedei chalitzah, and שרה Sarah can
take the שטר shtar and she could now go get remarried. How
do we know that's true for sure? Maybe it wasn't the brother-in-law?
No, because the בית דין beit din would never have done it
had they not known that it was the brother-in-law. Okay? So you
got the scenario? Because of the בית דין's beit din parameters, if
it happens in a בית דין, beit din, we know it's good.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, משום mishum now, now
משום דחוששין לבית דין טועין. mishum de-chosheshin le-veit din to'in. So the
גמרא Gemara said, I'm sorry, get miun ve-af al pi she-ein makirin,
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, לאו משום דחוששין לבית דין טועין? lav mishum
de-chosheshin le-veit din to'in? Now what is the reason that we don't
say, wait a minute, why do we start by limiting the בית
דין? beit din? Why don't we say a בית דין beit din
can do a חליצה chalitzah even if they don't know the people?
You can't write a שטר, shtar meaning it'll change whether you're allowed
to write a שטר. But if this guy is flying off to
China and we don't know if he's the brother-in-law or not, let's
just let him do the חליצה chalitzah and we'll figure it out
later. Why don't we allow that? Okay, and then אלי Eli and
I can't write a שטר by seeing it because all we know
is that they did it, we don't know that it was valid.
But why can't we allow that? So the reason we can't allow
that is that we're afraid that another בית דין beit din will
hear that they did a חליצה chalitzah and they won't know, hey,
we have to make sure we know the identity of the people.
They'll assume if they did a חליצה, chalitzah, it definitely was good.
Okay, so that's חשינן לבית דין טועין. chashinan le-veit din to'in. So
do you understand the parallel here? We're saying I'm allowed to write,
אלי Eli and I can write a שטר that so-and-so said something
on his deathbed that Jenna owed him $1,000, and we're not afraid
that another בית דין beit din will see the שטר and think
that it means that we're testifying to the veracity of the fact.
But a בית דין beit din can't do a חליצה chalitzah without
knowing the parties because they're afraid that another בית דין beit din
will hear they did a חליצה chalitzah and assume they did know
the parties. Why don't we say no, let the other בית דין,
beit din, if we're not afraid that בית דין beit din will
make mistakes, we shouldn't be afraid of it in either case. So
the גמרא Gemara says there's a difference. The גמרא says לא, בית
דין בתר בית דין לא דייקי, beit din batar beit din lo
dayki, בית דין בתר עדים דייקי. beit din batar edim dayki. A
court does not feel it has to check into the details of
what another court did. So if I just hear that another court
did a חליצה, chalitzah, I'm going to say, wait, maybe they didn't
have the right brother-in-law? Right? No. It's actually a nice thing. It's
like, you know, this type of, you know, mutual respect sort of,
which is completely what's absent nowadays, you know, where every בית דין
beit din is second-guessing every other בית דין, beit din, you know,
with עגונה agunah cases and whatever. Right? Here it's like a בית
דין beit din did it, I'm not going to ask questions. Maybe
it's even... not just like I'm going to... like maybe there's even
like a reason to sort of, you know, it's not my place
to ask questions, I assume what a בית דין beit din did
is correct, etc. So therefore, a בית דין beis din can't say
we're just going to do the חליצה, chalitzah, we'll let the next
בית דין beis din figure out if they were the right people
or not. Okay? Because the next בית דין beis din will assume
if a בית דין beis din did it, everything was okay. But
if the witnesses heard the שכיב מרע shachiv meira say something, and
a בית דין beis din gets a שטר that says the שכיב
מרע said X, Y, and Z, the בית דין beis din is
going to say, that's okay, fine, that's what those two witnesses said,
now we have to look into the facts, okay? But we're not
going to re-investigate what another בית דין beis din did. So it's
a really interesting issue about whether we assume בתי דין batei din
will be sloppy or not. And the גמרא says we assume that
they won't be sloppy, but we assume that they will, part of
I think as a principle probably, make a choice not to look
into the specifics of how another בית דין beis din acted. Okay?
So maybe we could all take a little מוסר mussar from that.
All right. We'll end with this. What? יהי Yehi with the חול,
chol, what do we say? See, do write or they don't?